<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="2.5.3">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2015-12-06T06:52:07+00:00</updated>
<id>http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/</id>
<subtitle>Random things that catch my eye that don&#39;t have a natural home elsewhere.
</subtitle>
<author>
<name>Lawrence Woodman</name>
</author>
<entry>
<title>One Month into Say Something in Welsh Course</title>
<link href="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/one-month-into-say-something-in-welsh" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Month into Say Something in Welsh Course" />
<published>2015-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2015-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/one-month-into-say-something-in-welsh</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/one-month-into-say-something-in-welsh">&lt;p&gt;I have just completed Challenge 13 of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.saysomethingin.com/welsh/&quot;&gt;Say Something in Welsh&lt;/a&gt; course and am really happy with my progress so far.  I am pretty pushed for time so have to take the opportunities to study when I can, but generally get in at least 20 minutes a day.  It has helped that I have had a lot of decorating to do recently and have therefore been able to get in an hour or so of study on decorating days, while improving the house at the same time.  This has been particularly good as I have been forced to do without the pause button and therefore it has encouraged me to speed up and just go with it.  The other time I have been able to study is while exercising, although I have found this harder as the sentences have been getting longer and more complicated.  The concentration on both has been too much at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe class=&quot;pull-right&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 2em;&quot; width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kIFwmkxch3U&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have posted a video on YouTube so that I can see how I am progressing; I have found it quite enlightening to hear me speak.  At the moment I very much sound like an Englishman saying Welsh words, so I need to concentrate on my pronunciation and prosody.  As the course progresses I think I am getting better at differentiating between hearing sounds that can sound similar such as &lt;em&gt;th&lt;/em&gt; (/ð/) and &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; (/v/), this has meant that I have had to relearn some of the words I had misheard earlier.  I’m also not sure if I’m pronouncing the ll (/ɬ/) sound correctly and I need to learn how to roll my R’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my speaking practise has been going well, I can’t say the same for listening.  I have rather neglected the daily listening exercises and as I haven’t been doing them regularly haven’t been able to make out all that much coherently.  It probably hasn’t helped that the last listening download was in northern Welsh, while I have been studying southern Welsh.  I have however taken the opportunity to listen to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/radiocymru&quot;&gt;BBC Radio Cymru&lt;/a&gt; in the car and in the background sometimes at home.  While I miss most of the listening exercises recorded at double speed, I have been pleasantly surprised at my ability to pick-up on bits of conversation on the radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all the SSiW course has been excellent.  The SSiW relies on frequent intense practise which is important to reinforce the vocabulary and by putting pressure on you to create a sentence it allows you to practise many more ways of using the vocabulary you have learnt by forming lots of different sentences.  This also encourages the quick natural response used in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that really demonstrates to me how friendly and inclusive the course and community surrounding it are is the way they have approached the question of where people are from.  When the course taught how to say where someone was from, the first example given was not ‘I am from Wales’ as you would expect, but ‘I am from England’.  This was followed if memory serves me correctly with ‘I am from America’ and ‘I am from Australia’, before finally getting to Wales.  This really pleased me as I felt a little bit of internal tension when the topic started with ‘where are your from’ as it reminded me that despite some Welsh heritage, I am essentially an Englishman and things have not always been easy between our two nations.  The approach taken overcame this and in a way reinforced what I have long thought: that it is strange that Welsh isn’t taken up by more people outside of Wales, with little or no Welsh heritage.  I think that the SSiW course could change this and help people view the language as of interest in its own right, in the same way that other minority languages, such as Icelandic, are studied by people with no personal connection.  Judging by the forum and the places from which people are studying Welsh, this seems to be happening.  Hopefully this will allow more people to enjoy and appreciate the unique and distinctive Welsh culture and raise Wales’ position both in the UK and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to learn to read Welsh and see more written down as then I could quickly look things up, particularly when phrases are said that have lots of similar sounds close together.  There are also times when I can read but not listen to audio and the extra practise would, I think, help reinforce what I have been learning and speed up my progress.  I intend to get &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/113896039X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=113896039X&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=lawrencewoodman-21&quot;&gt;Colloquial Welsh: The Complete Course for Beginners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ir-uk.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=lawrencewoodman-21&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=2&amp;amp;a=113896039X&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;, which I hope will complement the SSiW course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also enjoy being able to watch videos on YouTube building up from simple Welsh to more complex use of the language and will investigate what is available.  I think this would be particularly good to use where I have done my SSiW practise in the day and would like to do a little extra in the evening at a more relaxed pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found it quite useful recording the video above and putting my thoughts down in this entry and will report back in another month or so with my further progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="Language Learning" />
<category term="Welsh" />
<summary>I have just completed Challenge 13 of the Say Something in Welsh course and am really happy with my progress so far.  I am pretty pushed for time so have to take the opportunities to study when I can, but generally get in at least 20 minutes a day.  It has helped that I have had a lot of decorating to do recently and have therefore been able to get in an hour or so of study on decorating days, while improving the house at the same time.  This has been particularly good as I have been forced to do without the pause button and therefore it has encouraged me to speed up and just go with it.  The other time I have been able to study is while exercising, although I have found this harder as the sentences have been getting longer and more complicated.  The concentration on both has been too much at times.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Change of Plan, I’m Learning Welsh</title>
<link href="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/10/18/change-of-plan-im-learning-welsh" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Change of Plan, I&#39;m Learning Welsh" />
<published>2015-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
<updated>2015-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
<id>http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/10/18/change-of-plan-im-learning-welsh</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/10/18/change-of-plan-im-learning-welsh">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I announced that &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german/&quot;&gt;I was going to learn German&lt;/a&gt;.  However, before I started a few things came up.  In particular I stumbled across an online course called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.saysomethingin.com/welsh/&quot;&gt;Say Something in Welsh&lt;/a&gt;.  I have long toyed with learning Welsh as my maternal grandparents were born in Wales (Brynmawr and Maesteg) and as a child I remember enjoying learning the few bits of Welsh that they knew.  I don’t know much about their parents but can remember my great grandmother who spoke Welsh and am pretty sure I remember stories of other relatives who spoke Welsh.  I often listen to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/radiocymru&quot;&gt;BBC Radio Cymru&lt;/a&gt; and, despite not knowing what they are saying, enjoy the sound of the language and much of the music played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really encouraged me to think more seriously about switching from German to Welsh was a YouTube video posted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/laoshu505000&quot;&gt;Moses McCormick&lt;/a&gt;.  He mentioned how before he chooses to learn a language he looks in his area to see how many people speak it and what his opportunities to use it will be.  I have lived in Bristol for about 20 years and have only ever heard German spoken once, whereas I have frequently bumped into people who speak Welsh and my family frequently holiday in Welsh speaking areas of Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my working life I come across a Welsh speaker at least once a fortnight in a situation in which it would be ok to exchange pleasantries in Welsh, however I rarely have contact with German speakers where it would be appropriate to use German.  I was torn between learning German or Welsh but have decided because I will have more opportunities to use Welsh and because there is more support for learning it near me that it would be fun to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;say-something-in-welsh&quot;&gt;Say Something in Welsh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said above I found the ‘Say Something in Welsh’ course, which is what I am using to learn Welsh.  I read what people were saying about the course, tried the first lesson and fell in love with it.  I am going through the South Wales version of the course and am really enjoying it; I particularly like the accent and style of the man who presents it.  It could best be described as a high intensity course where once the presenter teaches you a new word or phrase in Welsh they then say lots of different phrases in English that you then have to say in Welsh.  The English phrases are combinations of the things that you have already learned with the repetition of those spaced.  So you could be asked to say the following sorts of phrases in order: “I have forgotten what I wanted to say”, “I have forgotten how to say what I wanted to say”, “I have forgotten to say what I need to say in Welsh”, etc.  It really piles on the pressure, but at the same time I feel that I’m making progress and the time has been well spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been doing it for about a week now and am really happy with how it’s going.  It has taken me a little longer to get to where I am now because there are two versions of the course: Course 1,2,3 or Level 1,2.  I started doing the ‘course’ versions of the course then added the ‘level’ versions, now I have switched to the level versions completely as they are the new framework and by keeping to just one version of the course the spaced repetition should work better.  My main difficulties at the moment are pronouncing the ‘ll’ sound, rolling my r’s and letting go of the pause button.  I am getting better at the latter, but not sure if I am pronouncing the right sound for the double l.  I think rolling my r’s will come naturally with practise.  Also occasionally it is hard to work out what consonant is being pronounced at the start or end of some of the words as the course encourages you to not read Welsh until later on as it is believed that your accent will be better without it.  This is probably true, but sometimes I have to use Google translate to try to find a word to clarify how they are saying it.  It’s a minor problem and I’m looking forward to finding some time later today to crack on with the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="Welsh" />
<category term="Language Learning" />
<summary>A few weeks ago I announced that I was going to learn German.  However, before I started a few things came up.  In particular I stumbled across an online course called Say Something in Welsh.  I have long toyed with learning Welsh as my maternal grandparents were born in Wales (Brynmawr and Maesteg) and as a child I remember enjoying learning the few bits of Welsh that they knew.  I don’t know much about their parents but can remember my great grandmother who spoke Welsh and am pretty sure I remember stories of other relatives who spoke Welsh.  I often listen to BBC Radio Cymru and, despite not knowing what they are saying, enjoy the sound of the language and much of the music played.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>I Have Decided to Learn German</title>
<link href="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Have Decided to Learn German" />
<published>2015-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
<updated>2015-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
<id>http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german">&lt;p&gt;I have wanted to learn to speak another language for a long time, but have either lacked motivation, commitment or felt that I didn’t have the time.  I have also had trouble deciding which language to learn as there are a few that I’m interested in for different reasons.  I have decided to post about it on this blog as it may be of interest to people to see the journey.  I’m 38 and from the UK.  The UK has a really bad record as far as learning foreign languages and people often say that learning languages is something best done when young.  I think the latter is just an excuse and the former has more to do with attitude and how we learn/don’t learn languages here.  Once I succeed it may motivate others to do the same and learn from the process I went through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reasons-for-learning-german&quot;&gt;Reasons for Learning German&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a few reasons for choosing German and reflecting on these has helped me to chose this language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I often come across German on the internet as there is a lot of activity in German surrounding some of my computing interests.  In particular vintage computers, which I blog about on &lt;a href=&quot;http://techtinkering.com&quot;&gt;TechTinkering&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of my favourite films are in German: Downfall (German: Der Untergang), Das Boot, Good Bye Lenin!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My wife and I had a great time in Germany when we visited Frankfurt once.  We liked the people we met, the food we ate and the environment we were in.  It is a country we really want to return to and explore more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eddie Izzard talks about how Europe is described as a ‘melting pot’ and how if the UK is to feel a part of it we need to melt a little.  I 100% agree.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like the sound of the language.  Which I know isn’t something said often, in fact people more often say the opposite.  However, I have heard it spoken with great tenderness and also appreciate the power that it can evoke when used with conviction.  To me it sounds like a direct language that gets to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have been enjoying some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLz8hJApSemQOIc1i6Y0QoBVEHnfTqQIy1&quot; title=&quot;Deutsche Musik Playlist on YouTube&quot;&gt;German music&lt;/a&gt; recently.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are lots of great resources for learning German.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where I live there are a number of regular social events for those interested in German language and culture, so once I get up to speed there are easy opportunities to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previous-language-learning-experience&quot;&gt;Previous Language Learning Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried a few times to learn another language and my experience is listed below in order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At school I took French and got an F at GCSE.  I never really engaged in the class and towards exam time I ignored it all together to concentrate on other subjects which I wanted to get better results in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I took a short Spanish class at the local college in the evenings.  I enjoyed this but never took it any further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago I started half-heartedly learning German through a Tech Yourself book.  I didn’t get that far but ever since I have been surprised how I have been able to glean a limited understanding of bits of German I have seen.  I stopped learning German so that I could concentrate on the Classical Greek which I studied next.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I studied Classical Greek at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.open.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Open University&lt;/a&gt; and scored very well.  After completing the Greek course I took courses in other subjects, started my own business and had children, by the time I was ready to continue studying Greek with the OU the follow-on course had unfortunately been withdrawn.  I would like to go back to studying Greek, but at this time in my life learning a spoken language trumps it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-start&quot;&gt;Where to Start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I begin I need to get a few things in order and make time to study, which to a certain extent is procrastination, but also because I have very little free time and don’t want to take too much on at once.  Finally I need to gather my German language learning resources.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="German" />
<category term="Language Learning" />
<summary>I have wanted to learn to speak another language for a long time, but have either lacked motivation, commitment or felt that I didn’t have the time.  I have also had trouble deciding which language to learn as there are a few that I’m interested in for different reasons.  I have decided to post about it on this blog as it may be of interest to people to see the journey.  I’m 38 and from the UK.  The UK has a really bad record as far as learning foreign languages and people often say that learning languages is something best done when young.  I think the latter is just an excuse and the former has more to do with attitude and how we learn/don’t learn languages here.  Once I succeed it may motivate others to do the same and learn from the process I went through.</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
