<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lawrence Woodman</title>
  <subtitle>Random things that catch my eye that don't have a natural home elsewhere.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io"/>
  <updated>2018-06-16</updated>
  <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/feed.xml</id>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/lawrencewoodman/tekyll">teykll</generator>
    <entry>
      <title>Book Review: The Reading Lesson - Teach your child to read in 20 easy lessons by Michael Levin and Charan Langton</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2017/06/12/the-reading-lesson-teach-your-child-to-read-in-20-easy-lessons/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2017/06/12/the-reading-lesson-teach-your-child-to-read-in-20-easy-lessons/"/>
        <published>
          2017-06-12
        </published>

        <updated>
          2017-06-12
        </updated>

        <summary>I used this book to teach both of my children to read before they started school.  My youngest completed it the day before his fourth birthday and could then read many of the Dr. Seuss books with little help.  My wife and I love reading and it has been wonderful to be able to teach my children to rea</summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Books Read in 2016</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/books-read-in-2016/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2017/01/01/books-read-in-2016/"/>
        <published>
          2017-01-01
        </published>

        <updated>
          2017-01-01
        </updated>

        <summary>Another year and another list of books I read in the year.  I only read 9 books in 2016, but am happy to have finally read 'The Canterbury Tales'.  As usual these aren't proper reviews, instead they are a nice handy way of keeping a list of the books I have read easily accessible.
On War by Carl von </summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Ten Months into Learning Welsh</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2016/07/31/ten-months-into-learning-welsh/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2016/07/31/ten-months-into-learning-welsh/"/>
        <published>
          2016-07-31
        </published>

        <updated>
          2016-07-31
        </updated>

        <summary>I finished level 1 of Say Something in Welsh about five months ago and was pleased with the results.  It feels like a very natural way to learn a language and the course is great but left me unsure about the pronunciation of some words.  In particular it is hard to differentiate sometimes between f (</summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>One Month into Say Something in Welsh Course</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/one-month-into-say-something-in-welsh/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/one-month-into-say-something-in-welsh/"/>
        <published>
          2015-11-18
        </published>

        <updated>
          2015-11-18
        </updated>

        <summary>I have just completed Challenge 13 of the Say Something in Welsh course and am really happy with my progress so far.  I am pretty pushed for time so have to take the opportunities to study when I can, but generally get in at least 20 minutes a day.  It has helped that I have had a lot of decorating t</summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Change of Plan, I'm Learning Welsh</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/10/18/change-of-plan-im-learning-welsh/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/10/18/change-of-plan-im-learning-welsh/"/>
        <published>
          2015-10-18
        </published>

        <updated>
          2015-10-18
        </updated>

        <summary>A few weeks ago I announced that I was going to learn German.  However, before I started a few things came up.  In particular I stumbled across an online course called Say Something in Welsh.  I have long toyed with learning Welsh as my maternal grandparents were born in Wales (Brynmawr and Maesteg) </summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>I Have Decided to Learn German</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/i-have-decided-to-learn-german/"/>
        <published>
          2015-09-27
        </published>

        <updated>
          2015-09-27
        </updated>

        <summary>I have wanted to learn to speak another language for a long time, but have either lacked motivation, commitment or felt that I didn't have the time.  I have also had trouble deciding which language to learn as there are a few that I'm interested in for different reasons.  I have decided to post about</summary>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Books Read in 2015</title>
      <id>https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/01/01/books-read-in-2015/</id>
      <link href="https://lawrencewoodman.github.io/blog/2015/01/01/books-read-in-2015/"/>
        <published>
          2015-01-01
        </published>

        <updated>
          2015-01-01
        </updated>

        <summary>The following is a list of the books I read and wrote brief reviews for in 2015.  I find book reviews hard to write, partly as I am reluctant to jot down notes as I read the book for fear of not fully immersing myself in the tale.  So while the reviews don't do the books justice, I do however, like t</summary>
    </entry>
</feed>
